Guide to the Center for Documentary Studies Neighborhoods Project records, 1997-2004 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Center for Documentary Studies Neighborhoods Project records 1997-2004 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies. Community Programs.
3 Linear Feet Approx. 1000 Items
The Neighborhoods Project was created as part of the Community Programs department within Duke's Center for Documentary Studies. According to the CDS website, it offered North Carolina elementary school teachers an innovative and effective way to meet social studies goals outlined in the state's standard course of study. The project provided a way to engage students in their own communities, focusing on their individual lives and stories through photographs, narrative writing, and storytelling. It provided a series of experiential learning activities that encouraged the use of photography, oral history, and narrative writing in an exploration of community and citizenship.
Collection includes black-and-white photographs, negatives, and slides from projects created by students at Durham's E.K. Powe and W.G. Pearson elementary schools between 1997 and 2004. The images document the social life and the built environment in Durham, N.C., in city neighborhoods where the students live; they feature children, pets, houses and places of business, groups of adults, and other neighborhood scenes where whites, African Americans, and Spanish-seeking citizens live. Some materials are in Spanish. Also includes some student booklets and publications highlighting their projects as part of the program. Acquired as part of the Archive for Documentary Arts.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted to educational, non-commercial use.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials requires production of listening or viewing copies.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Center for Documentary Studies Neighborhoods Project records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2011.
Historical Note
Adapted from a Center for Documentary Studies website:
The Neighborhoods Project, created by local teachers and Center for Documentary Studies (CDS) staff members, offered North Carolina elementary school teachers an innovative and effective way to meet social studies goals outlined in the state's standard course of study. The project provided series of experiential learning activities that allowed students to engage with their own communities, focusing on their individual lives and stories through photographs, narrative writing, and storytelling, and exploring ideas of community and citizenship.
The Neighborhoods Project received support from the Civic Education Consortium, the Z. Smith Reynolds Foundation, and the North Carolina Arts Council, an agency funded by the State of North Carolina and the National Endowment for the Arts. It was disbanded in 2010.
Collection Overview
Collection includes black-and-white photographs (a few are hand-colored), negatives, and slides from projects created by students at Durham's E.K. Powe and W.G. Pearson elementary schools between 1997 and 2004. The images document the social life and the built environment in Durham, N.C., in city neighborhoods where the students live; they feature children, pets, houses and places of business, groups of adults, and other neighborhood scenes. Also includes some student booklets and publications highlighting their projects as part of the program. Materials are sorted by school, with miscellaneous or unidentified materials in the last series. Also contains electronic and audiovisual recordings that require reformatting before use.
Acquired by the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies. Community Programs
African Americans -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Social conditions
Documentary photography -- Durham (N.C.)
Documentary photography -- North Carolina
Documentary photography -- Teaching and education
Elementary schools -- Durham (N.C.)
Youth programs -- North Carolina
Durham (N.C.) -- History -- 20th century
Durham (N.C.) -- Social conditions
Durham (N.C.) -- Pictorial works
North Carolina -- Social conditions
Audiocassettes
Photographs
Slides (photographs)
Negatives
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Related Material
The Neighborhoods Project was just one part of the Center for Documentary Studies Community Programs' initiatives, some of whose records are also held by the Rubenstein Library. Other related collections include:
Literacy Through Photography records, 1990-2000
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Durham Traditional Arts Survey Project records, 2000-2002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Youth Document Durham and Durham Works records
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Youth Noise Network Records
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- E.K. Powe Elementary School, 1999-2003, (1 box)
  - Negatives, 1999, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Negatives, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Slides and prints, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Slides, 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - Negatives and prints, 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - Negatives and prints, 2001, (6 folders) (Box 1)
  - Binder, 2002, (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Slides, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
  - Binder, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
  - Student booklets, 2000-2003 (Box 1)
  - Publications, 2002-2003 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
- W.G. Pearson Elementary School, 2002-2004, (.5 box)
  - Binder, 2002, (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Binder, 2002, (2 of 3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Binder, 2002, (3 of 3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Slides, 2003-2004 (Box 2)
  - Publications, 2004 (Box 2)
- Other Materials, 1997-2004 and undated, (2 boxes)
  - West End Photography project prints, 1997-1998, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Color prints and negatives, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Binder, 2004, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous slides, 2001-2004 and undated (Box 2)
  - Audiovisual and electronic materials (Box 3)
    Includes 16 audio cassettes, 10 floppy disks, and 2 zip disks.
    [Original audiovisual are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
    [Electronic records need to be migrated to a library server and screened for access before they can be used. To request access, please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
  - Old Five Points Neighborhood Project prints, circa 1997, (30 prints) (Box 4)
    Taken by students at an unidentified school and year. The last two black-and-white 8x10" prints have been hand-colored. Includes some captions created by the student photographers. Some of all of the images may have been exhibited at an Old Five Points exhibit at the CDS in 1998.